CURRICULUM VITAE

Jeffrey Hanson

Department of Biology, Carleton University, Ottawa, Canada

☐ jeffrey.hanson@uqconnect.edu.au ☐ jeffrey-hanson.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research concerns the challenges involved in conserving biodiversity. I am interested in understanding how areas can be managed to achieve conservation objectives for minimal cost. In particular, I specialize in operationalizing ecological and evolutionary processes to develop plans for protected area systems that maximize the long-term persistence of biodiversity.

EDUCATION

- 2013–2018 PhD, Biology, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Richard Fuller and Jonathan Rhodes, thesis: Conserving evolutionary processes.)
- 2011–2012 BSc (Hons), First Class, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Steve Salisbury, Craig Franklin, Hamish Campbell, and Ross Dwyer, thesis: *Using stable isotopes to assess the relationship between body-size, habitat use and diet in estuarine crocodiles* (*Crocodylus porosus*))
- 2007–2010 BSc, Major in Ecology, The University of Queensland, Australia

PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS

2019– present	Postdoctoral researcher at Department of Biology, Carleton University, Ottawa, Canada
2018-2019	Postdoctoral researcher at CIBIO/InBIO, Centro de Investigação em Biodiversidade e Recursos Genéticos da Universidade do Porto, Vairão, Portugal
2018	Freelance software developer contracted by Joe Bennett, University of Carleton
2012-2013	Research Assistant to Richard Fuller, The University of Queensland, Australia
2012-2013	Research Assistant to Jonathon Rhodes, The University of Queensland, Australia
2012	Casual Professional Staff, The School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, Australia

PUBLICATIONS

Journal articles

2020 **Hanson, JO**, Rhodes JR, Butchart SHM, Buchanan GM, Rondinini C, Ficetola GF & Fuller RA (2020) Global conservation of species' niches. *Nature*, 580: 232–234.

Hanson JO, Veríssimo A, Velo-Antón G, Marques A, Camacho-Sanchez M, Martínez-Solano Í, Gonçalves H, Sequeira F, Possingham HP & Carvalho SB (2020) Evaluating surrogates of genetic diversity for conservation planning. *Conservation Biology*, In press: DOI:10.1111/cobi.13602.

Hanson JO, Marques A, Veríssimo A, Camacho-Sanchez M, Velo-Antón G, Martínez-Solano Í & Carvalho SB (2020) Conservation planning for adaptive and neutral evolutionary processes. *Journal of Applied Ecology*, 57: 2159–2169.

Camacho-Sanchez M, Velo-Antón G, **Hanson JO**, Veríssimo A, Martínez-Solano Í, Marques A, Moritz C & Carvalho SB (2020) Comparative assessment of range-wide patterns of genetic diversity and structure with SNPs and microsatellites: A case study with Iberian amphibians. *Ecology & Evolution*, 10: 10353–10363.

Schuster R, **Hanson JO**, Strimas-Mackey M & Bennett JR (2020) Exact integer linear programming solvers outperform simulated annealing for solving conservation planning problems. *PeerJ*, 8: e9258.

Hanson JO, Fuller RA & Rhodes JR (2019) Conventional methods for enhancing connectivity in conservation planning do not always maintain gene flow. *Journal of Applied Ecology*, 56: 913–922.

Hanson JO, Schuster R, Strimas-Mackey M & Bennett JR (2019) Optimality in prioritizing conservation projects. *Methods in Ecology & Evolution*, 10: 1655–1663.

Ambrose L, **Hanson JO**, Riginos C, Xu W, Fordyce S, Cooper RD & Beebe NW (2019) Population genetics of *Anopheles koliensis* through Papua New Guinea: New cryptic species and landscape topography effects on genetic connectivity. *Ecology & Evolution*, 9: 13375–13388.

- 2018 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP & Fuller RA (2018) raptr: Representative and Adequate Prioritization Toolkit in R. *Methods in Ecology & Evolution*, 9: 320–330.
- 2017 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Riginos C & Fuller RA (2017) Environmental and geographic variables are effective surrogates for genetic variation in conservation planning. *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America*, 114: 12755–12760.

Mather AT, **Hanson JO**, Pope LC & Riginos C (2017) Comparative phylogeography of two co-distributed but ecologically distinct rainbowfishes of far-northern Australia. *Journal of Biogeography*, 45: 127–141.

Dudaniec RY, Worthington Wilmer J, **Hanson JO**, Warren M, Bell S & Rhodes JR (2016) Dealing with uncertainty in landscape genetic resistance models: a case of three co-occurring marsupials. *Molecular Ecology*, 25: 470–486.

Dhanjal-Adams KL, **Hanson JO**, Murray NJ, Phinn SR, Wingate VR, Mustin K, Lee JR, Allan JR, Cappadonna JL, Studds CE, Clemens RS, Roelfsema CM & Fuller RA (2016) Distribution and protection of intertidal habitats in Australia. *Emu*, 116: 208–214.

Hanson JO, Salisbury SW, Campbell HA, Dwyer RG, Jardine TD & Franklin CE (2015) Feeding across the food web: the interaction between diet, movement and body size in estuarine crocodiles (*Crocodylus porosus*). *Austral Ecology*, 40: 275–286.

Runge CA, Watson JEM, Butchart HM, **Hanson JO**, Possingham HP & Fuller RA (2015) Protected areas and global conservation of migratory birds. *Science*, 350: 1255–1258.

Auerbach NA, Wilson KA, Tulloch AI, Rhodes JR, **Hanson JO** & Possingham HP (2015) Effects of threat management interactions on conservation priorities. *Conservation Biology*, 29: 1626–1635.

Bunton JD, Ernst AT, **Hanson JO**, Beyer HL, Hammill E, Runge CA, Venter O, Possingham HP & Rhodes JR (2015) Integrated planning of linear infrastructure and conservation offsets. In Weber, T, McPhee, MJ & Andersson RS (eds) *MODSIM* 2015, 21st International Congress on Modelling and Simulation. Modelling and Simulation Society of Australia and New Zealand, December 2015, pp. 1427–1433.

Rabeb D, Othman DS, Essilfie AT, Hansbro PM, **Hanson JO**, McEwan AG & Kappler U (2015) Maturation of molybdoenzymes and its influence on the pathogenesis of non-typeable *Haemophilus* influenzae. *Frontiers in Microbiology*, 6: 01219.

Non-peer reviewed articles

- 2020 **Hanson JO** (2020) Conserving species' niches. Nature Ecology & Evolution Community, https://go.nature.com/2wCckAN.
- Beher J & **Hanson JO** (2015) Welcome to the Mapotron. *Decision Point*, **86**: 10–11.

PEER REVIEW ACTIVITIES

I have reviewed submissions to following journals: Austral Ecology, Conservation Letters, Diversity and Distributions, Ecological Applications, Global Change Biology, Journal of Applied Ecology, Methods in Ecology & Evolution, PLoS ONE, and Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences.

PRESENTATIONS

Conference presentations

- Hanson JO, Camacho-Sanchez M, Marques A, Martínez-Solano Í, Velo-Antón G, Veríssimo A, Carvalho SB (2019) Conserving evolutionary processes for three amphibian species in the Iberian Peninsula. Oral presentation to European Ecological Federation 15th Congress, Lisbon, Portugal.
- 2018 **Hanson JO**, Schuster R, Morrell N, Strimas-Mackey M, Watts ME, Arcese P, Bennett JR, Possingham HP (2018) prioritize: Systematic conservation prioritization in R. Oral presentation to UseR! 2018, Brisbane, Australia.
- 2016 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP, Fuller RA (2016) *RAPR: Representative* and Adequate Prioritizations in R. Oral presentation to Society for Conservation Biology 4th Oceania Congress, Brisbane, Australia.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Fuller RA (2014) Conservation planning for intra-specific biodiversity using surrogates. Oral presentation to the Meeting of the Minds miniconference at The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia.

EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES

Classroom Instruction, The University of Queensland, Australia

2013–2015 Professional tutor to the "Field Ecology" course, coordinated by Myron Zalucki

Workshop Instruction

- 2019 Spatial Conservation Prioritization: Concepts, Methods and Applications coordinated by Silvia Carvalho, Virgilio Hermoso, and Jeffrey Hanson at CIBIO/InBIO, Centro de Investigação em Biodiversidade e Recursos Genéticos da Universidade do Porto, Vairão, Portugal.
- 2017 Use of Machine Learning in Conservation, Moving beyond just Maxent and SDMs coordinated by Falk Huettmann at the 28th International Congress for Conservation Biology (ICCB), Cartagena, Colombia.

2015 Geospatial Analysis in R coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer, Rebbecca Runting and Jutta Beher at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.

Smoothing the Marxan Flow with R coordinated by Matthew Watts at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.

2013 Introduction to Geospatial Analysis coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.

Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis in R workshop coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.

2011 Introducing R coordinated by Simon Blomberg at The University of Queensland, Australia.

Seminars

2017 Systematic conservation prioritization in R presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.

2016 Biodiversity processes in reserve-selection presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.

Scientific meetings and networking events

2018 rOpenSci Unconference, Melbourne, Australia.

2017 R Unconference hosted by the Brisbane Users of R Group, Brisbane, Australia.

2016 rOpenSci Unconference, Brisbane, Australia.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

prioritizr An R package for building and solving conservation planning problems (https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=prioritizr).

oppr An R package for prioritizing funding for threatened species recovery projects and pest management project (https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=oppr).

wdpar An R package for downloading and cleaning data from the World Database on Protected Areas (https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=wdpar).

raptr An R package for generating spatial prioritizations that secure intra-specific variation (https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=raptr).

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

- Compute resource allocation by the National eResearch Collaboration Tools and Resources (NeCTAR) project (2017–2019)
- Postgraduate Travel Award Scholarship, The School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, Australia (2016)
- Australian Postgraduate Award (APA) Scholarship (2013)